[SPEAKER_01]: What is the escape from pain?
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people think it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people think it is pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure is the escape from pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they don't necessarily think that, though.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that's the only escape that they know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the only attitude that a person without a right view will have only one attitude towards pain, which is
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only means of escape that they know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either through trying to get rid of the pain, because that's more pleasant, or to actually finding some different pleasure to occupy yourself with, so you forget about the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you turn towards pleasure in order to avoid pain, because you can't deal with pain on its own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's what the, what the suttas say, that Bhutujana doesn't know any other escape from pain, other than sensuality, sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was saying before, like, the people are not attracted to sensuality just because it's pleasant and gives you that, you know, sweet taste or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're also dependent on it because that's the only means that their mind has of dealing with pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the prospect of sensuality, it's already something people depend on.
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility of getting pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: At least, pleasure is perpetually possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: I might be refraining from it, not engaging with sensuality, but I'm still using the possibility of pleasure as a relief from when the pain is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you still depend on the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can deal with this pain now, because there is a possibility in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a promise, a prospect of pleasure later on that will be greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's worth enduring this pain now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everybody, like, even when you want arahantship to be free from suffering, you still have the projected idea of pleasure through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the whole practice revolves around actually not removing your dependence on sensual pleasure as a mean of dealing with pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, removing your dependence even on the possibility of sensual pleasure as means of dealing with pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why when people heard the Buddha describe nibbāna to them, the patujanas in the suttas, they were... well, they were scared, because in their minds it was like, oh, that's basically a complete absence of joy, pleasure, the only form of joy and pleasure that an unenlightened mind knows, which is central pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in their minds, oh, this was like, this is the most depressing, miserable, dreadful thing that will kill me and destroy me, if that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: They were genuinely shocked, afraid by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gripped by anxiety and fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because mind that depends on pleasure... absence of pleasure means misery.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of pleasure does not mean pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means absence of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of pain as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, what those people were afraid of was just a pure neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither pleasant nor unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the mind that depends on pleasure, neither pleasant means painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter that it's not unpleasant either.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fact that it's not pleasant, for the mind that depends on pleasure, is terrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's terrifying not because in itself it's terrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's terrifying because you're refusing to give up your dependence on pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that fear feeds your dependence, which then makes you afraid, which then feeds the dependence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upādāna of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this neutral feeling, because of your
[SPEAKER_01]: Craving for pleasure is... it's just painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_00]: When neutral feeling is not known, not understood, not discerned, it could be felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you... you... you... nibbāna is the absence of joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's joyless.
[SPEAKER_00]: But joylessness does not mean misery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joylessness means equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joylessness means no joy and no pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means evenness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to value that, the mind needs to train to that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Needs to train for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you need to discern and develop wisdom in regard to the neutral feeling and then it will become the supreme peace of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing can match that peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the mind, it depends on pleasure, depends on prospect and uses at least the possibility of future pleasure as a means of relief in regard to the day-to-day pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that mind hears joylessness, that is automatically felt as misery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolute depressing, overwhelming pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not pleasant, but it's not unpleasant either.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't get to value the fact that it's not unpleasant either, because you're too concerned about... there is no joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the sense restraint needs to be done before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through sense restraint, you basically start training yourself towards joylessness of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, again, the root of sensuality, as the Buddha said so many times, is your delight in the joy that you get on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the beautiful or tasty objects in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: The root of sensuality is your dependence on that type of pleasure, nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remove that dependence on that pleasure and you will find peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: So sensory strain is physically preparing you, withdrawing you from that pleasure, so that mentally you can see
[SPEAKER_00]: How gratuitously you depend on it and then choose to withdraw yourself because, ah, this is not worth clinging to, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're not physically withdrawn, you will never mentally be able to, like, stop depending on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sense restraint means basically emulating nibbāna, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Emulating the non-dependence on joy that's acquired through senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you need to start doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you still want to have it mentally, physically, at least, you need to be withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Verbally, you need to be withdrawn.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eventually, mentally, you'll be able to do so as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, once you start withdrawing yourself from that engaging in pleasures, then, what will naturally occur is that experience of mutual freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start withdrawing yourself physically from pleasures, that's already training
[SPEAKER_00]: For you to be able to endure the neutral feeling and not freak out in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, only people that are not withdrawn bodily, verbally, mentally from sensuality, lose their mind when they recognize what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that will kill me, that will destroy me.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you already have been cultivating sense restraint, saying no to yourself, taming your senses, practicing sense control, it's not going to be as frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: The joylessness of nibbāna
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll be something you can actually get closer to, as opposed to lose your mind, fall on the ground, pull your hair, beat the breasts in despair, like, oh, that will kill me, as they did when the Buddha would clearly show what nibbāna, what his teaching is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, that's why it's always said, like, like those who are free from passion, they have no, like, fear even in face of death, because that's what death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation of these senses upon which, well, upon
[SPEAKER_00]: which pleasures I depend.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those who are free from passion, even when these senses are threatened, there is no fear, because there is no passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: I... there is no dependence on the pleasure of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the absence of passion means no fear of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means no fear of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means no fear of dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean... Means peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depression doesn't mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depression, it's only generated from the point of view you still depend on the pleasure, and now you found something that fully, like, crushes that dependence, removes it, and there is no more future of it, and that is scary, because you refuse to give it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because neutral feeling in itself is scary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's joyless, but it's also... there is... but that all... that doesn't mean it's miserable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, absence of joy and absence of misery.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a... absence of ambitious and like a thirst inspiration for achievement and absence of depression.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Arahants in the Sutta would say in the Terra Terrigata, I delight not in life.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no delight towards anything in this life, through the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I delight not in death either.
[SPEAKER_00]: I await my time.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the Arahant's declaration.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that description of the fourth jhāna, that's the, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: Perfect, complete, surmounting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your equanimity, you know, upekasati, is... but it's the surmounting of that pleasure and pain and joy and grief in regard to the world and disappearance of that pleasure and pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely steadied mind in a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the first jhāna, it's already... From the point of view of non-jhāna, first jhāna, it's like steadying your mind in a neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neutral from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you can go even further and refine that neutral feeling up to the point of full jhāna equanimity.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even the first jhāna starts by abandoning joy and grief in regard to the world and unification of the mind that comes on account of thinking and pondering and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that in itself, it's felt pleasantly, in a sense of a neutral peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neutral feeling, when understood, it's felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the suttas say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neutral feeling, when not understood, it is felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's the understanding, your knowledge, your discernment of it, determines how you're going to feel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, joylessness, when understood, it's pleasant, because there's no disturbance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joylessness, when not understood, it's miserable, dreadful, anxious, overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you prepare yourself to endure it, that which is overwhelmingly anxious and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: By starting the sense restraint, by seeing the danger in the slightest fault, by being watchful, mindful, careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already practicing strength to be able to endure the neutral feeling, which is initially going to try to scare you, and then you train yourself to that, and this passion is being developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, it comes back to also the other talk we did on non-activity, non-engagement, fear of boredom that people have, fear of nothing to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether they practice Buddhism or not, maybe everything just becomes another thing I do to keep myself occupied, because otherwise I get overwhelmed by the neutrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, boredom is truly just neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's the most dreadful thing for every mind that's not developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the more understanding you're gaining, the more pleasurable it becomes, that neutral feeling, that absence of joys.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that, you know, arahant's feelings are some like mystical dimension.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's just three types of feeling, whether you're a Kutujan or an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just how much influence those three types of feeling have over you, and your decisions, and your views, and your assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or whether you're free from views and assumptions in regard to these feelings, and then, in the felt, there's just the felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the seen, there's just the seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Heard, just the heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the feeling that's felt, you're neutral in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no pressure means, truly, there's really no feeling there anymore, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kutujana's feelings are gone in an arahant, but that doesn't mean that arahant has no aggregative feeling anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can arahant feel without feeling, seeming contradiction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, develop understanding of a neutral feeling, and you'll see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the same like when Sariputta declared, oh, what a pleasure, what a pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Dāyana, I think, in the suttas, asked him, what do you mean, what's pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, nibbāna, it's pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, didn't you on another occasion say, nibbāna, there is nothing felt?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, yes, and that's what is pleasant, the fact there's nothing felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the understanding of there's no feeling here, it's very agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it all boils down to development in regard to the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, in order for you to begin even any development in regard to neutral feeling and being able to endure it and withstand it, you need to stop habitually giving in to the pleasant feeling and feeding the thirst for more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have to habitually stop giving in to the feeding of the unpleasant feeling to try to get rid of it, resisting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: By doing these two things, you are equipping yourself to endure neutrality, that's felt neither pleasantly, but not unpleasantly either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarifying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: By enduring it, you, as I said, you're becoming more familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, non-activity, enduring the initial anxiety of boredom, and finding value in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even that's what we would say, like the solitude,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's for somebody who has developed wisdom to start finding pleasure in solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it's terrifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without wisdom, solitude, mind cannot bear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, the Buddha did outline what you need to prepare beforehand, so that you can benefit from solitude, which is impeccable virtue, seeing the danger in the slightest fault,
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, jhānas, but, you know, they usually come with solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense restraint, right view, all these things, you develop beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you go to forest, remote dwellings, where there's only wild animals living and so on, your mind will not overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be benefiting from it, the neutrality of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if you're in a position where there's nothing to do, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to be top of the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, top, like a remote forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Empty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or an empty hut.
[SPEAKER_01]: Empty of activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Empty of activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Empty of distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Empty of others turning as they please.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, physically removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, apartment will do just fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do want to have the environment that will support that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, don't think that that will do the work for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be ready for the solitude if you've already practiced sense restraint in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have already endured joys and griefs in regard to the world without acting out of it habitually.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you surmount it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by running into the solitude or hiding in the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes, yeah, people try to contrast this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, see, the Buddha said we should go to the remote dwellings and so on, because they don't want to deal with their own sense restraint and stuff here.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's like the second group of herd, deer herd, from that sutta, that we did also recently, that shuns the bait and runs atop a mountain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's no wisdom developed there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sense restraint, in regard to the world, in regard to the central poles, in regard to dependence on the joys and so on, needs to be developed and needs to be endured.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be painful because... not because of the sense restraint, but because of your dependence on joys of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you suffer when you first restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't suffer because you say no to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You suffer because... You've been saying yes to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you've been saying yes all this time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, saying no to yourself just reveals your addiction, your dependence on these gratuitous sensual joys.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you're responsible, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you're fully feeding, maintaining, adding to, proliferating.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practice towards joylessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: When joylessness is understood, it's the utmost peace, agreeability, it's nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joy means... joylessness means no delight, no delight in anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it also means no misery and being unable to be miserable or scared or affected by any type of pain on account of anything, including impending death, dying, you know, terminal diagnosis or whatever else, which eventually will have to occur.
[SPEAKER_01]: No more prospect of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, things that are being... will be destroyed by death,
[SPEAKER_00]: are not things you depend on anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you removed your dependence on gratuitous joy that came out of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You removed your delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So joylessness, that's why you'll die before you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Become joyless and you will be unable to be miserable as well.